um all right what about cs-50 um despite
my feelings about Harvard and I League
schools which are a total sham uh more
than 60% of people that go to IA League
schools are people who have never had to
take a test in their life to be able to
get pass entry because their family went
there and so I have I should probably do
a whole video on that
um but cs50 is free right and a lot of
people have been recommending
cs50 um the way it worked when I last
evaluated which was more than five years
ago was you would pay to get the
certificate you didn't have to pay to go
through the material but you had to pay
to get the
certificate um and the fact that you
have to pay to get the certificate in
the credential is up to you um again
there's another video on getting a job
and how you you get a job by
establishing trust I need to do a lot of
other videos on this but there's one
that's been made already that getting a
job is about trust and if that
credential if that piece of paper is
going to establish trust with your
potential employer depending on what
you're going for which completely
depends on your plan and your job tons
of videos on that um you need to know
all that up front then cs-50 could be a
very
nutritious uh you know offering on the
buffet of educational resources
available to you and you're putting the
the items in the buffet on your plate
right um I consider cs50 to be some of
the most nutritious of the educational
Buffet offerings out there uh David
David he's pretty fun um the guy who
teaches it he you know he's I I don't
like his style but a lot of people
really like it and they think he's
amazing um I just to me he comes off as
a Harvard person and and that is very
distracting but I I watched all of the
cs50 thing probably back in 2017 I want
to say it was a long time ago and most
of cs50 is actually run by the
Tas um I mean they have a they obviously
have a big budget but the most the most
important reason to consider doing cs50
eventually um is be two reasons really
uh one is the the content it it the
content is spot-on relevant uh to
getting started in computer science
right um it's not practical though
nothing that you're going to learn in
cs50 is going to get you a job it's just
not it's going to help you understand
computers and
programming uh but it's not going to
it's not going to directly help you get
a job but again I still feel like for
the same reason I suggest you should
learn C for understanding uh which you
can do you know working through the book
uh and get a similar amount of of
expertise um in fact if you were so to
keep with our metaphor here um if you're
coming up to the educational buffet and
you see cs50 there and you see you know
head for c um I would go for head for C
first and I would you know eat
that and then I would maybe add in cs50
and uh so let's talk about what's in it
um uh cs50 is uh what if I remember I
don't know if they still do this but
they used to start with scratch and they
would have or blockly what whatever
version of it it is it's a thing where
you drag you drag around blocks to to
write code and they're not the only U
professional University level um
organization that does uh blockley they
still do that yeah and the the
motivation and the the understanding of
that is this is going to help you think
there's there one of the reasons I don't
like any of the computer science kind of
things is because they focus overly on
something called um computational
thinking and I need to do a whole video
on computational thinking but the short
version is as summarized by the guys who
created um uh Co what is it co combat
how much they hate the term because it
is especially in 2013 it became
uh a buzzword for anything that helped
you think like a computer right and the
person in who wrote The Blog which I
totally agree with was making the the
argument that foreign language and
Mathematics and a bunch of other things
help you think logically uh help you
with computational thinking which is
just the ability to organize your
thoughts into algorithms and procedures
and stuff and the argument is there's
many ways to do that so why would I
bring this up because the reason that
organizations like cs50 and Harvard and
everybody use blockley and these
absolutely totally completely useless
languages um is to get you starting to
think like a computer and and I don't
buy that I I don't buy it um that said I
have a story I have a story you like
stories okay so we're going to talk
about all the languages that the cs50
teaches and how they teach it and and
that will help you make a decision um
and and you can tell me if it's changed
since since 2017 or whatever so um one
of the most brilliant people that ever
came to my door and and I mean
absolutely raw Baseline
intelligence um they came to my door and
their their mom said we just can't keep
up we can't keep our son uh challenged
and we're so glad to find you would you
mind evaluating him and I told the story
before but I'm going to tell this is a
great time to tell the story so um this
person came in and after about 20 or 30
minutes uh of just sitting with them and
the mom went across to the pub I
think she's super nice and um and so he
he said I said well tell me what you've
been doing what is your you know what
are your goals he goes well I've been
all I've got been working on is scratch
I this this should probably go on a
scratch and what about scratch video
I'll probably say the story again and
what about scratch video but whatever um
so anyway this
guy um proceeds to and I'm going to
summarize because I'm going to put that
in another video he proceeds to show me
the biggest scratch board I've ever seen
and I mean it was if if you know about
visual programming uh on scratch you
know that you have to have you have to
be able to zoom in and out to see the
whole thing right so it was like Google
Earth zooming out to see the whole world
because he had so much stuff in there
this this kid had done things in scratch
because that had been the his only
method of writing code uh for something
like two or three years and he had done
things that I have never seen I've never
seen anybody and it was his only thing
so in during the rest of our hour
together I showed him python I showed
him the roer enty parts of python on the
terminal and he immediately the first
thing he wrote was was he did his own uh
Pythagorean theorem uh function in
Python that was the first thing he
wanted to do he didn't he didn't want to
make things move on the screen he didn't
want to make you know a silly game the
very first thing he did and we're
talking about a kid who was like 10
years old 10 or 10 or 11 years old he
wasn't even in I think he had maybe had
pre-algebra already but um and by the
way algebra you know before there
there's before algebra and there's after
algebra and all the people that I've
helped learn coding it's a Monumental
once they get fun once they start
thinking functionally um coding is
breeze it's like easy to pick up after
that um yeah and so uh so the point it
is that this once he learned about
Python and you know an actual language
uh he didn't he didn't want to even look
at scratch anymore right and and I I
believe that
cs50 uh does that they don't
spend um a lot of time on Scratch and it
sounds to me Dan saying there it's it's
still the same order that it was when I
evaluated it it goes from scratch and
then straight into C which seems really
weird right because C is a really really
lowle language and I think the reason
they do that is to show you the ultimate
and high level languages I mean scratch
is probably one of the highest level
languages there is and then C which is
you know the second lowest level
language you can write in besides
assembly and um and then they put python
in there and then they turn SQL to do
because it's a declarative language and
HTML HTML CSS and JavaScript HTML and
CSS I like that they do that because
HTML and CSS are both declarative
languages and J s is a is a procedural
language so I do like it's kind of
interesting that they did put SQL in
there um and and that I mean that for
for a com for somebody who's trying to
teach you computer science very strictly
speaking Computer Science teaching you
the difference between declarative and
and procedural languages this really
good idea um about understanding
computer science in general um which by
the way people complain all the time to
be a sub video about this you I get a CS
degree
I mean you'll get you'll be really good
at understanding how computers work
that's what it is you might not be able
to get a job though because you're not
being taught how to use a computer to
produce code and solutions that are
going to get you a job that you just
aren't you're being taught how computers
work really well you might end up coming
out of it writing your own computer
language you know which is cool and all
might prove how smart you are but it
doesn't do anything with regard to
solving a specific problem for a
specific business and that's how you get
a job
um and uh plus they do the python web
framework um so um so
my I think cs50 is a rather nutritional
offering on the buffet of educational
resources out there um do I think that
it's worth buying the certificate
probably not uh again it all depends on
the target career you're going for and
specifically the target organization you
may try to to get I've done a whole
video on this but they're depending on
the organization they might see that
cs50 degree and they'll see that you you
know took the effort to do it and that's
cool right but you know if you got to
weigh that against being able to say um
here is a
project you know this is a web API
project that I made that does something
I like whatever that is could be Pokemon
for God's sake you know a registry of
all the Pokemon out there there's
already a pokedex by the way um and you
know what what what do what is going to
produce the most level of trust with
your potential employer uh a passion
project that does all the same things
that demonstrates you used those tools
or a piece of paper from cs50 that says
you understand the difference between a
procedural and declarative language and
you finished all the
homework I it's up to you to decide but
most employers want want the experience
over the piece of paper most of them not
all there there are definitely places
that will take uh that will take the
piece of paper over that yeah you can
buy the sht from edex uh a digital copy
of free if you I don't yeah uh the best
Al turn to learn the basics in computer
and computer science um I've already
said this there's already other videos
on this um so I'll just refer to that
but other than to say the best
alternative to computer science
programming courses is actual experience
building things you care about that
prove you want to do that thing and
can't can do that thing right and if if
if you've already decided if you've
already decided that your career is
going to be a software developer backend
front end mid-range you should already
have made that decision or you should
already have sampled some of the work in
that area to find that out and not only
that you should also have targeted one
of five computers I'm sorry not
computers one of five employers that you
want to go work for and you and this is
in the beginner boost this is there's
other videos earlier videos in the
beginner boost about this these are all
in skills. and they talk about these
essential steps before decide before you
build your learning curriculum before
you start filling your plate of learning
resources from the pipe you need to know
that stuff upfront so before you even do
that and a lot of people that ask me
this question what do you think about
this this this they're they haven't done
that yet so please please make sure you
understand those very very difficult
steps that need to be done uh I've done
a lot of videos about that and how I
came I mean the one video about X
mission where I had to change from
Russian to um to computer I'm sorry from
from Russian to something I I couldn't
work in Russian anymore my wife wouldn't
let me my first wife and and so I had to
change jobs and I called up xmission and
I said what's the number one skill I
could learn that would make it so that
you had to hire me on the spot I I'm
thank you for your time they let me talk
to an engineer they said learn Pearl I
learned Pearl in 20 days I got the book
I set forward a very strategic learning
plan um and I got the job I not for them
for another company that paid me three
times what I was making at the at the
tour guide company they actually
apologize for not paying me more money
because I set about I I knew I wanted to
do internet things I was like oh this is
really fun well I how do I work for an
internet service provider so I called
one up that all that stuff is in other
videos right that activity where you
define what you want to be and where you
want to be what you want to be that has
to happen before you start filling your
plate of educational resources because
you're going to make a mistake if you
don't I've been saying this over and
over and over again because people make
this mistake all the time and U that
includes cs50 right what what is cs50
getting you what is it getting you and
who cares about cs50 you're well I don't
know who whoever whoever my employer
eventually is going to be I'm sure
they're going to like it right how do
you know that you don't even know you
don't even have a random sampling of
potential employers that you would like
to consider which is something you
should have you should already have made
a very short list of like you know five
to 10 potential employers and you should
be specifically working on a strategy to
get a job at either one of those
specific companies or a company like
them and that will shape everything else
your educational choices your choice of
of personal learning networks how you're
going to seek out people and learn to
meet them when you meet them on the
street you're like hey you're one of the
people on my five on my on my list of
five companies tell me all about your
job and what you do because everything
in your and not to mention your
manifesting powers it's a very hippie
term but you know you're you're now you
you're visualizing where you're going to
be and where you're going to work and
and and and you know as soon as I called
up that next mission and I talked to the
engineer I was like I want to be that
engineer and I had something mentally to
latch on to I'm going to be an engineer
like that guy and I never met that
person but I was grateful for them for
taking the time whether that happens
because you cold call a place that you
want to work for or you meet them at a
random meet up this is they separate
videos on this but
cs50 doesn't apply until you know that
right do you I mean God if I if I had
talked to this engineer and say do you
think cs50 will help me get a job here
they'd be like he would have laughed at
me like no learn we need you to learn
Pearl they don't teach do they teach
Pearl and N CS no they teach scratch and
C they learn well that's cool and all
but we're not hiring
you I'm sorry that's how the way that's
the way it goes